<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>


<annotation-spec>

  <doc>
    This annotation specification was specifically developed to code
    postural/gestural events from TV session of the "Literarisches
    Quartett" where four literary critics discuss a number of recently
    published books. This scheme is thus suited for a group of sitting
    people where the seating facillities are immobile.
  </doc>

<!-- **************** HEAD ********************** -->
 
 <head>
  <valuetype-def>

   <valueset name="audiencePhaseType">
     <value-el color="#eeee00">rise</value-el>
     <value-el color="#ee8800">hold</value-el>
     <value-el color="#00bb33">fall</value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="gestureType">
     <value-el color="#8cda8e">beat</value-el>
     <value-el>deictic</value-el>
     <value-el>emblem</value-el>
     <value-el>iconic</value-el>
     <value-el>metaphoric</value-el>
     <value-el>adaptor</value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="deicticType">
     <value-el>
     addressee
     <doc>
     Subject points to addressed person/object.
     </doc>
     </value-el>
     <value-el>
     space
     <doc>
     Subject points somewhere in gesture space, points to nothing
     concrete that is present in the room.
     </doc>
     </value-el>
     <value-el>
     self
     <doc>
     Subject points to him/herself usually by putting the hand
     on his/her chest.
     </doc>
     </value-el>
     <value-el>
       person
       <doc>
         A present person other than the speaker or addressee.
       </doc>
     </value-el>
     <value-el>
     audience
     <doc>
     Points at audience, usually in a circumscribing motion.
     </doc>
     </value-el>
     <value-el>
     self+addressee
     <doc>
     Points to himself and to addressee.
     </doc>
     </value-el>
   </valueset>


   <valueset name="phaseType">
    <value-el color="#eeee00">
      prep
      <doc>
        Preparation phase, bringing arm and hand into stroke
        position. Note that changing hand shape before/after moving
        the arm belongs to the preparation, too. Also code position
        info.
      </doc>
    </value-el>
    <value-el color="#dd0000">
      stroke
      <doc>
        The most energetic part of the gesture movement. <b>Encode all
        other attributes for this gesture phrase in the stroke
        element!</b>
      </doc>
    </value-el>
    <value-el color="#aa0044">
      beats
      <doc>
        Only for non-beat gestures! A number of successive strokes
        (beats); all strokes should be covered by this phase. If there
        is a hold in-between then continue with prep.
      </doc>
    </value-el>
    <value-el color="#ee8800">
      hold
      <doc>
        A phase of stillness just before or just after the stroke,
        usually used to defer the stroke so that it coincides with a
        certain word. <b>When annotating an element as "hold" do not
        annotate any other attributes!</b>
      </doc>
    </value-el>
    <value-el color="#ee00ee">
      recoil
      <doc>
        Directly after the stroke the hand may spring back so as to
        emphasize the harshness of the stroke.
      </doc>
    </value-el>
    <value-el color="#00bb33">
      retract
      <doc>
        Retraction. Movement back to rest position. In sitting
        position this is usually the arm rest, the lap or folded
        arms. <b>Encode no other attributes in a "retract" element.</b>
      </doc>
    </value-el>
    <value-el color="#00aa66">
      partial-retract
      <doc>
        Retraction movement that is stopped midway to open another
        gesture phrase. Code position info here.
      </doc>
    </value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="emblemType">
	<value-el>
	  anticipation
	  <doc>
	    Anticipation of evil or warning or threat. Open hand
	    waving near own head/ear as if preparing to slap
	    someone. Verbalization: "Oh wait!", "I see it coming", "O
	    my!"
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  attention
	  <doc>
	    Index finger held motionless in the air to emphasize the
	    importance of what is said, seen or heard. (German:
	    "erhobener Zeigefinger").
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  block
	  <doc>
	    A gesture of total refusal ("No way!"), blocking
	    suggestions/arguments made or expected ("No matter what, I
	    don't accept/believe/do this."). Usually, palm toward
	    addressee, moving like along a wall in front of the
	    speaker either with palm facing the addressee or with
	    index finger.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  chide
	  <doc>
	    A gesture of warning ("watch out!"), reprimand ("That was
	    bad of you!") or attention ("Note this!"). Usually done
	    with outstretched index finger wiggling in the air.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  concession
	  <doc>
	    A gesture of partial concession ("You are right but..."),
	    pre-emptive defence ("I know you won't like this but...")
	    or pre-emptive pacification ("I don't mean to disrespect
	    your opinion but..."). Movement usually consists of
	    showing the insides of your hands (palm down), like in a
	    "hands up" gesture of surrender (defensiveness!).
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  despair-threat
	  <doc>
	  Display of exaggerated despair or threat by lifting both
	  arms with elbows out and fingertips almost touching the
	  forehead. Verbalization: "what am I to do!", "jesus!", "this
	  is so bad!". Often ironically used: "o yes, this is soooo
	  bad!" - implying that someone overreacted.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  doubt-shrug
	  <doc>
	    A gesture indicating doubt ("I wouldn't count on that."),
	    ignorance ("I don't know.") or indifference ("I don't
	    care."). Movement consists of showing the insides of your
	    hands (palm up) and is usually accompanying by a raising
	    of the shoulders (shrug).
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  dismiss
	  <doc>
	    A gesture like waving off a little boy or a pet, like
	    haughtily dismissing a submitted person. As opposed to
	    dump, more like waving off a little annoyance (a fly)
	    without much emotional display (rather disgust than anger).
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  finger-ring
	  <doc>
	    A sign where the index finger meets the thumb, other
	    fingers spread out or relaxed, usually signalling fine
	    quality, good taste etc. In a more metaphoric sense it
	    means that the matter is very subtle, that the reasoning
	    is very precise/sharp. Note that the same gesture is used
	    by conductors.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  hand-clap
	  <doc>
	    One hand slaps the other hand from. Verbalization: "What
	    luck!", "well, now!", "good!", "so...".
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  hand-rub
	  <doc>
	    One hand rubs the other hand. 
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  hands-up
	  <doc>
	    Both hands are raised, palms facing front. Literally
	    taken, a gesture of surrender, showing lack of weapons
	    (nothing to hide) and opening up body.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  indignation
	  <doc>
	    Both arms are raised, hands open, palms upwards. Shoulders
	    are up and tense, and the face displays
	    anger. Verbalization: "O come on!", "Now pull yourself
	    together, will ya!". The gesture indicates one's losing
	    temper/patience, as if provoked by a child's constant
	    hassling.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  invitation
	  <doc>
	    Both arms are opened wide, hands open with palms towards
	    addressee(s). Verbalization: "Welcome!", "You are invited
	    to...", "I have nothing to hide". A gesture demonstrating
	    cooperation, open-mindedness, open-heartedness, opening of
	    one's own defences and innocence.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  knee-slap
	  <doc>
	    Hand(s) are slapped on knee(s) to signal something
	    envigorating happening or incite other people to be
	    active. Verbalization: "let's go", "well, now!", "good!",
	    "so...". Variant: one hand slaps the other hand from high
	    above (not like normal clapping) - looks like the knee
	    version, only that one hand replaces the knee.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  more-or-less
	  <doc>
	    Hand(s) wiggles, palm down, eyes are slits to indicate an
	    effort to estimate something. Verbalization: "more or
	    less", "about/around", "approximately".
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  number
	  <doc>
	    Fingers indicate a number. One finger (thumb or index
	    finger) indicates number one, two fingers indicate number
	    two etc.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  one-hand-other-hand
	  <doc>
	    Verbalization: "on one hand... on the other hand". Usually
	    motioning with hand, fist, finger, arm in one direction,
	    then in the other.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  pray
	  <doc>
	    Verbalization: "please" or "God/Heavens! Please!". Usually
	    putting both hands together either flat or locked, still
	    or shaking, eyes raised to heaven (or superior).
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  purse
	  <doc>
	    Referring to hand shape: index finger and thumb touch and
	    point upward, hand performing an up-and-down
	    movement. Meaning is culture specific. In LitQua used for
	    emphasis. Verbalization: "Ey!", "Hey!".
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  quivering-doubt
	  <doc>
	    Hand, palm down, quivers a little from side to side to
	    negate something or express doubt. Verbalization: "don't
	    know", "not at all", "that's not right", "not exactly".
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  refusal
	  <doc>
	    Verbalization: "no, thanks", "no", "really not". Waving
	    hand/palm/index finger toward addressee, usually at a low
	    level and with low intensity. Refusing idea, proposal,
	    offer with a certain amount of politeness but can look
	    condescending.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  so-what
	  <doc>
	    Signalling the provocation for an answer from a (possibly
	    imaginary) interlocutor which obviously cannot be given
	    because the answer is insinuated to be
	    absurd/incredible/childish. Verbalized as "So what!" or
	    just "So...?". Often performed by showing the palms and
	    shaking the head with raised eyebrows. When used while
	    recounting something it indicates that the content is
	    trivial or obvious or blurry. Verbalizations: "or
	    something like this", "or God knows..."
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  surprise-hands
	  <doc>
	    Signalling some unexpected event.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  two-sided-doubt
	  <doc>
	  Signalling that something (a) may not be right, or (b) is
	  subtly two-sided. Performed by showing palm up and then
	  turning the hand that palm is down, and then flipping back
	  and forth. Verbalization: (a) "I don't know", "rather not"
	  (b) "pretty complicated", "not that easy".
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  wipe
	  <doc>
	    A gesture intending to stop something/one ("Let's end
	    this"), indicating a break ("He stopped doing it.") or
	    signalling dismission ("Let's forget about it"). Movement
	    parallel to the floor like wiping a table.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  wave
	  <doc>
	    A gesture for getting attention, with open relaxed hand(s),
	    palm towards addressee/audience. Verbalization: "hey!",
	    "here!", "look here!"
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="metaphoricType">
        <value-el>
	  conduit
	  <doc>
	    The actual object or idea is treated as a material
	    substance that can be presented in a cupped hand or as a
	    larger object held with two hands.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  conduit-emerge
	  <doc>
	    A movement indicating a substance coming up, breaking
	    through a surface upward. Hands usually dig somewhere and
	    mimic throwing it in the air. This is not a "change"
	    metaphoric, though if this movement were to be continued
	    it could become one. So this one halts abruptly.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  conduit-fling
	  <doc>
	    Metaphoric object is thrown with some power at the final
	    place. Refers to the motion of the gesture. Note that this
	    motion includes the RELEASE of the conduit object, i.e. an
	    actual object would fall to the floor. Otherwise, it is a
	    normal conduit.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  conduit-flip
	  <doc>
	    Hand(s) indicate(s) that the substantialized topic is
	    suddenly brought up/presented by showing the palm
	    (presenting the topic/item) in a flipping movement. Very
	    frequent. Unclear whether this should be treated as a
	    beat.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  conduit-fitting
	  <doc>
	    A movement that indicates that the subject fits together
	    or does not fit together. A substance is shown and a
	    movement of compressing the substance is performed.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  conduit-open
	  <doc>
	    Open fist with emphasis.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  conduit-snatch
	  <doc>
	    Metaphoric object is snatched out of the air like an
	    insect und often held for same time.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  conduit-sphere
	  <doc>
	    Movement indicates a spherical shape. Usually performed
	    when taking a wider perspective, talking about a "whole".
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
          clockwork
	  <doc>
	    Mental processes are seen as a clockwork with wheels, one
	    of which is turned by a gesture close to the head with one
	    or both hands.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  beam
	  <doc>
	    Stems from the idea that a gaze is like a beam originating
	    from one's eyes.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  bridge
	  <doc>
	    Finger or hand makes a curved line like a bridge. Refers
	    to a logical step or the next item in a sequence.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  change
	  <doc>
	    Usually circular, rotating movement indicating change or
	    progress.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  heart
	  <doc>
	    Usually a shovelling motion like shoving a substance from
	    the heart region to the surface. Referring to emotional
	    states.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  hold
	  <doc>
	    A motion of grabbing a bell-jar (Käseglocke) like thing
	    which encompasses the subject at hand. Is actually a conduit.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  idea
	  <doc>
	    Motion indicating an idea springing from one's (fore)head,
	    done with a finger or a hand (or two).
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>
	  aura
	  <doc>
	    Hand indicate a spherical aura around one's head or
	    body. Refers to processes of the mind like thinking,
	    wondering, non-understanding, madness.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="iconicType">
        <value-el>rectangular</value-el>
        <value-el>spherical</value-el>
        <value-el>semi-spherical</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  planarPF
	  <doc>
	    Movement on the plane that is parallel to the speaker's
	    front, i.e. the plane defined by a wall standing in front
	    of the speaker.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  planarPFloor
	  <doc>
	    Movement on the plane that is parallel to the floor.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  big
	  <doc>
	    Hands indicate large size of an object/concept.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  drink
	  <doc>
	    Hands act as if bringing a glass to the lips in order to
	    drink.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  explosion
	  <doc>
	    Hands fly in different directions to depict something big,
	    forceful, incredible, great.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  sway
	  <doc>
	    Hands go up and down, each in turn, e.g. left up, right down. 
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  small
	  <doc>
	    Using index finger and thumb to show small distance.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
	<value-el>
	  strength
	  <doc>
	    Making fists to express aggression, force, strength.
	  </doc>
	</value-el>
        <value-el>away-motion</value-el>
        <value-el>falling</value-el>
        <value-el>grabbing</value-el>
	<value-el>pantomime</value-el>
        <value-el>writing</value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="gspaceHeightType">
     <value-el>above-head</value-el>
     <value-el>head</value-el>
     <value-el>chest</value-el>
     <value-el>belly</value-el>
     <value-el>waist</value-el>
   </valueset>
   <valueset name="gspaceLateralType">
     <value-el>middle</value-el>
     <value-el>left</value-el>
     <value-el>right</value-el>
     <value-el>sym-middle</value-el>
     <value-el>sym-center</value-el>
     <value-el>sym-outer</value-el>
     <value-el>sym-extreme</value-el>
     <value-el>symmetrical</value-el>
     <value-el>asymmetrical</value-el>
     <value-el>outer-left</value-el>
     <value-el>outer-right</value-el>
     <value-el>extreme-left</value-el>
     <value-el>extreme-right</value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="headshiftType">
      <value-el color="#eeff00">
        raise
	<doc>
	  Chin rises.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el color="#ffaa00">
        lower
	<doc>
	  Chin lowers.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el color="#eeff55">
        raise+turn
	<doc>
	  Diagonal movement.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el color="#ffaa55">
        lower+turn
	<doc>
	  Diagonal movement.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el color="#aaff00">
        sideways
	<doc>
	  Tilting (German: kippen) the head toward one side.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el color="#ee00ee">
        turn
	<doc>
	  Rotation of the head. Do not confuse with rotation of the
	  body! A good indicator for the initiation of a head turn is
	  an eye-blink.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el>
        nod
	<doc>
	  This is an <b>emblem</b>. It is therefore distinguished from
	  a mere raise-lower sequence by assuming the intention to
	  nod.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el>
        shake
	<doc>
	  Also an <b>emblem</b>. Therefore distinguished from a mere
	  turn-turn sequence by assuming the intention to shake.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="rstdirType">
     <value-el color="#ffaa00">
       backward
       <doc>
         Marked span is related to previous span.
       </doc>
     </value-el>
     <value-el color="#9900ee">
       forward
       <doc>
         Marked span is related to following span.
       </doc>
     </value-el>
   </valueset>

   <valueset name="topicType">
    <value-el>introduction</value-el>
    <value-el>book-content</value-el>
    <value-el>book-discussion</value-el>
    <value-el>author</value-el>
    <value-el>discussion</value-el>
   </valueset>
   <valueset name="bodypartType">
    <value-el>forehead</value-el>
    <value-el>hair</value-el>
    <value-el>cheek</value-el>
    <value-el>eyes</value-el>
    <value-el>eyebrow</value-el>
    <value-el>nose</value-el>
    <value-el>ear</value-el>
    <value-el>mouth</value-el>
    <value-el>neck</value-el>
    <value-el>shoulder</value-el>
    <value-el>chest</value-el>
    <value-el>arm</value-el>
    <value-el>hand</value-el>
    <value-el>leg</value-el>
    <value-el>knee</value-el>
    <value-el>lap</value-el>
    <value-el>hair</value-el>
   </valueset>
   <valueset name="touchmotionType">
    <value-el>tap</value-el>
    <value-el>stroke</value-el>
    <value-el>pinch</value-el>
    <value-el>pick</value-el>
    <value-el>scratch</value-el>
   </valueset>
   <valueset name="handshapeType">
    <value-el>open-flat</value-el>
    <value-el>open-spread</value-el>
    <value-el>halfopen-flat</value-el>
    <value-el>halfopen-spread</value-el>
    <value-el>fist</value-el>
    <value-el>finger-ring</value-el>
    <value-el>purse</value-el>
    <value-el>index-out</value-el>
    <value-el>thumb-out</value-el>
   </valueset>
   <valueset name="handednessType">
    <value-el>both</value-el>
    <value-el>left</value-el>
    <value-el>right</value-el>
   </valueset>
   <valueset name="emphasisType">
     <value-el color="#eeff00">strong</value-el>
     <value-el color="#ffaa00">moderate</value-el>
     <value-el color="#aaff00">reduced</value-el>
   </valueset>

  </valuetype-def>
 </head>

<!-- ************************* BODY ******************** -->

 <body>
  <track-spec name="take" type="primary">
    <doc>
      This track records the take, i.e. the view of the camera on the
      scene. I use this track to see where the speaker of interest is
      <b>not</b> in the picture, i.e. in a file where Reich-Ranicki is
      of interest I will only annotate those takes where RR in not in
      the picture.
    </doc>
    <attribute name="visible">
      <doc>
        The actual person/group seen in the take.
      </doc>
      <value-el color="#eeee00">
        Reich-Ranicki
	<doc>Also known as: the Pope of literary critique.</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el color="#dd5500">Karasek</value-el>
      <value-el color="#ee00ee">Löffler</value-el>
      <value-el>invited guest</value-el>
      <value-el color="#00dd00">
        all
	<doc>
	  Panoramic view on all four speakers.
	</doc>
      </value-el>
      <value-el color="#ee8800">audience</value-el>
      <value-el color="#aa5500">book</value-el>
      <value-el>other</value-el>
    </attribute>
  </track-spec>

  <track-spec name="trl" type="primary"
              color-attr="emphasis">
    <doc>
      This track contains the transliteration of the spoken
      discourse. The <b>token</b> attribute contains the word or sound
      uttered. There are a number of special marks signified by
      squared brackets like [breath] or [aeh] for the mark-up of
      nonverbal sounds. Note that there is <b>no syllable
      information</b>.
    </doc>
    <attribute name="token">
      <doc>
        Words and nonverbal sounds.
      </doc>
    </attribute>
    <attribute name="emphasis" valuetype="emphasisType">
      <doc>
        Emphasis of this word. Possible values are the same as in
        SABLE.
      </doc>
    </attribute>
  </track-spec>
    
 <group name="ling" collapse="true">    
   <doc>
     Groups all tracks with linguistic information. The tracks
     typically refer to the trl track.
   </doc>
   <track-spec name="i-phrase" type="span" ref="trl">
     <doc>
       Models the intonation phrase. This is a very fine segmentation
       employed here taking into account different features to
       identify a border (consult Stefan Baumann for details).
     </doc>
     <attribute name="type">
       <doc>
         There are different recurring patterns in the intonation
         contour and other, more technically oriented,
         distinctions. This dimension mixes some aspects but is still
         informative.
       </doc>
       <value-el>
         copy
	 <doc>
	   The intonational contour of the preceding intonational
	   phrase is reused for effect.
	 </doc>
       </value-el>
       <value-el>
         repair
       </value-el>
       <value-el>
         abandoned
       </value-el>
     </attribute>
   </track-spec>
   <track-spec name="rst" type="span" ref="trl"
               color-attr="direction1">
     <doc>
       Shows Rhetorical Relations coded with Mick O'Donnel's tool and
       imported here. The hierarchy is flattened, the direction
       indicates whether the current span was related to a previous or
       a following span.
     </doc>
     <attribute name="relation1">
       <doc>
         Relation that is closer to the leafs of the RST tree. This
         relation has therefore more relevance to this particular
         span.
       </doc>
     </attribute>
     <attribute name="direction1" valuetype="rstdirType">
       <doc>
         Tells which direction in the known RST scheme this relation
         is pointing to.
       </doc>
     </attribute>
     <attribute name="relation2">
       <doc>
         This relation is higher up in the tree, i.e. closer to the
         root. Its meaning may therefore be more abstract (and
         hidden?).
       </doc>
     </attribute>
     <attribute name="direction2" valuetype="rstdirType">
       <doc>
         Tells which direction in the known RST scheme this relation
         is pointing to.
       </doc>
     </attribute>
   </track-spec>

 </group>

  <group name="gesture">
    <doc>
      This group clusters all so-called gestures which are really <b>arm
      and hand gestures</b>. The members of this group give a functional
      view on gesture. Overlap is only possible with beats that can
      occur in any type of gesture. Look at description of <b>phase</b>
      values to see how that is coded.
    </doc>

    <track-spec name="phase" type="primary" >
      <attribute name="type" valuetype="phaseType">
      <doc>
        My phase description is based on the phases postulated by
        Kendon and McNeill (1992), later on extended by Kita et
        al. (1999).
      </doc>
      </attribute>
      <attribute name="trajectory" valuetype="TimestampedPoints" >
	<config-spatial>
	  <connections type="off" color="blue" transparency="0.5" size="2" />
	  <marker numbering="on" color="yellow" transparency="0.5" size="5" filled="false" />
	</config-spatial>
      </attribute> 

      <attribute name="handedness" valuetype="handednessType" />
    </track-spec>

    <track-spec name="phrase" type="span" ref="gesture.phase">
      <attribute name="category" valuetype="gestureType" display="true" />
      <attribute name="emblem type" valuetype="emblemType" display="true" />
      <attribute name="metaphoric type" valuetype="metaphoricType" display="true" />
      <attribute name="iconic type" valuetype="iconicType" display="true" />
      <attribute name="correlate" valuetype="MultiLink" />
      <attribute name="deictic where" valuetype="deicticType" display="true" />
      <attribute name="adaptor where" valuetype="bodypartType" display="true" />
      <attribute name="copy gesture" valuetype="Boolean" display="true" />
      <attribute name="certainty" valuetype="Number(0,6)" />
      <!-- <attribute name="open number" valuetype="Number" /> -->
    </track-spec>


    <track-spec name="group" type="span" ref="gesture.phrase">
      <attribute name="name" valuetype="String" />
    </track-spec>

  </group>

 </body> 



</annotation-spec>
